Guide to the Harman V. S. Peeke Papers (Record Group No. 185)
Yale University Library
Divinity School Library
Harman V. S. Peeke Papers,
1887-1987
Peeke, Harman V. S.
Record Group No. 185
Total archival boxes 2; total linear footage 1'
Detailed and substantive quarterly letters and writings document the missionary work of Harman V. S. Peeke and his wife Vesta G. Peeke. The Peekes were missionaries in Japan from 1893 to 1929, serving under the Reformed Church in America.
Yale University Divinity School Library 409 Prospect Street New Haven, CT 06511 Email: divinity.library@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-5301
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Provenance
Gift of the Peeke family.
Historical Sketch
Harman Van Slyke Peeke and Vesta Greer Peeke were missionaries in Japan, serving under the Reformed Church in America. H. V. S. Peeke first sailed from New York to Tokyo in 1887 and returned to the U. S. in 1891. Vesta Greer sailed from New York in 1887 to become a missionary in China but married HVSP in 1893 and thereafter served in Japan. The Peekes had seven children. H. V. S. Peeke's mission work included teaching, evangelism, and mission administration; he became notably expert in the Japanese language. From 1920 to 1926 the Peekes were at Meiji Gakuin, an educational institution in Tokyo. They returned to the U.S. for the last time in 1929. Harman died of cancer on November 27, 1929 in Holland, Michigan.
Description of the Papers
This collection is most notable for the substantive quarterly letters in Series I. These letters were written primarily by Harman V. S. Peeke during the Peekes' years in Japan, 1893 to 1929. The letters, addressed to "Dear Friend," are primarily in typescript mimeographed format; some holograph letters have been transcribed by the Peeke family. The letters provide detailed descriptions of Peekes' work and observations on life and events in Japan. Information provided by the Peekes' circular letters is supplemented by numerous articles written by Peeke. The collection also includes two published works by Peeke related to use of the Japanese language.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings of H.V.S. Peeke
III. Writings of Others
IV. Collected and Personal Material
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Peeke, Harman V. S.; Missions --Japan.
Authors
Peeke, Harman V. S.
Occupations and Functions
Missionaries
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Circular letters of Peekes
    - Scrapbook volume #1: Quarterly letters - Series I. No. 1 to Series I No. 12; (from Kagoshima, Japan; also includes annual reports of Kagoshima Station, South Japan Mission, R.C.A for 1895,1897), 1893 Dec - 1896 Oct (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook volume #2: Quarterly letters - Series I. No. 13 to Series II. No. 14; (1897 - 1903 Jun from Kagoshima; 1903 Oct - 1904 Apr from Saga), 1897 Jun - 1904 Apr (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook volume #3: Quarterly letters - Series II. No. 15 to Series V. No. 17; Series V. No. 26 to Series VI. No. 2 (1904 - 1916 from Saga; 1919 - 1920 Apr from Shimo Osaki Machi, Tokyo; 1920 Aug - 1926 from Meiji Gakuin, Shirokane, Tokyo; 1927 Jan - Jul from Oita; 1927 Oct - 1929 Jan from Beppu; 1929 from Holland, Michigan), 1904-1926, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Typed transcripts of circular letters, 1893 Dec -1907 Jul (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - Of others
    - Glen Bruner to Olive Peeke, 1933 Sep (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cheryl Peeke Edelen to/from Reischauers, 1987 Feb (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Writings of H. V. S. Peeke, Series II
  - "My Trip to Korea" - journal and typed transcript, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A First Reader for Home Students of the Japanese Language, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Kai - How to Conduct Meetings in Japanese, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook of articles written by HVSP for Japan Evangelist and The Christian Movement in Japan; reviews of his two books, 1904-1921 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Writings of Others, Series III
  - "Social Service and Christian Appalachia", "The Missionary and Industrial Work" by Isabelle McCausland (niece of Mrs. Peeke), 1922, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "The Church of Christ in China" by Mary Sue Rohwer (granddaughter of Peekes) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Cheryl's Peeke into Japan" by Cheryl Peeke Edelen (granddaughter of Peekes), ca. 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Collected and Personal Material, Series IV
  - Photographs: portraits of HVSP, VGP; mission house in Saga; campus of Meiju Gakuin, Tokyo; photocopies of photos from Edelens' trip to Japan in 1987, 1887- 1987 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Japan Evangelist issue [contains articles by HVSP], 1923 Sep-Oct (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Diary of H. V. S. Peeke describing his first term in Japan, 1887- 1892 (Box 2, Folder 24)